You know, when a man is living,
He wants to live life to the fullest.
A feeling of sad dignity comes over him, and that's fatal for a comedian.
I am at peace with God.
My conflict is with man.
He is in tune with his times.
He denounces things.
He made films that not everyone liked.
So it had to be eliminated.
His talent was never seduction.
but that of conviction.
Such a one of the German Volkes applauds when they hear the words of Juden,
den Todfeinden seiner Rasse.
He is a man who loves women.
And that's a sin in America.
The most reactionary part of American culture attacked Chaplin.
Good evening,
It's here.
at the Manoir de Ban,
about thirty kilometers from Lausanne,
on the shores of Lake Geneva,
that Charlie Chaplin lived the last 30 years of his life.
He was in exile at the time.
with his wife and their 8 children.
Regardless of your age,
You know Charlo,
its silhouette,
his approach,
his adventures that have enchanted the world ever since exactly
100 years.
However,
Many of you know almost nothing about the one he created and embodied,
Who was Charlie Chaplin really?
What was his true face behind Charlo's?
Where does it come from?
Where did he get this inspiration?
Chaplin,
It is, of course, cinema and its genius.
But he is also a man of the century.
a story that spans two world wars
the rise of Nazism,
the Great Depression and the Cold War,
and of which Chaplin was a witness.
the critic and sometimes even the victim.
Why will he have to leave Hollywood?
Fleeing the United States, considered an enemy of the state?
Why will he be monitored?
Listened to by the secret services of several countries?
And this will continue until the end of his days.
A life lived.
of shadow and light.
A story that begins in the London saffron fields in the 19th century and will end here in Vevey in the 1970s.
It is in this house that everything begins tonight in 1972, when Chaplin had been living in exile for 20 years.
That day,
Charlie Chaplin has just received an unexpected letter,
An invitation to an honorary Oscar in Hollywood.
He expected anything but this.
He hasn't been back to the United States for 20 years.
driven out of this country like an enemy of the state.
Giving him an Oscar,
It was "Thank you,
Mr. Chaplin,
Excuse us,
"Mr. Chaplin"
That was it.
Hollywood regretted everything that had happened.
and really wanted to be forgiven.
Since 1952,
Charlie Chaplin lived in seclusion.
here,
in this large manor house on the shores of Lake Geneva,
with his wife Una and their eight children.
He had a very difficult time leaving the United States.
and at 82 years old,
He's not sure he wants to revive those bad memories.
He felt fragile.
He didn't know how to introduce himself.
how we would view it.
And he had bad memories.
bitter memories of what he had endured,
to wonder how it would be received.
But Ouna insists that he accept.
She knows Chaplin better than anyone.
She knows that he has been dreaming of this moment all his life.
It was his homeland,
That's where he spent his whole life.
That represented,
apart from all the resentment he had.
It still meant something to him.
So Chaplin finally agreed.
worried about confronting those who consider him an enemy of America,
but with the desire to show the world that genius is still alive.
I didn't want it to be a charity.
This is not charity.
He says it's the biggest event in theatrical history.
I am not interested in the events.
but I would like a chance to show them that I'm not in the know yet.
At the same time,
in the United States,
The FBI receives numerous anonymous letters.
On April 10, 1972,
It is an anxious Charlie Chaplin who is rediscovering the city of Los Angeles.
He experienced his early career there.
his successes,
but also his setbacks.
He wants to see again these streets that he walked through for 40 years.
He was curious to see how Los Angeles had changed.
But it quickly depressed him.
He said there were only banks,
Banks and more banks.
Chaplin asks to pass by his old film studio.
Since his abrupt departure in 1952,
He doesn't know what became of him.
He thought they would have demolished it.
that they would have built a shopping center instead.
But no,
It was just as he had left it.
Actually,
The studio has been declared a national monument.
The city turned it into a museum and he knew nothing about it.
Chaplin remains in the car,
observe from a distance.
while inside,
Everyone is waiting for it.
They had put up banners and objects bearing Charlie Chaplin's image, hoping to lure him inside.
But it was too difficult for him.
Overwhelmed by emotion,
He collapses in tears in the car and begs the driver to take him home.
I'm not surprised he didn't want to visit the studios.
He had such strong memories of it when it was full of life.
He then passes through Hollywood Boulevard.
this avenue of stars where every celebrity has their star.
Chaplin's is ablaze in its execution.
It was added just a few weeks before her return.
Up to this point,
Hollywood deemed one of the greatest geniuses of cinema unworthy of its famous boulevard.
Finally,
Chaplin attends a garden party organized in his honor by a friend of his wife.
All of Hollywood is here.
But behind the smiles,
He seems a little lost.
He doesn't recognize anyone.
He is airy in the midst of this crowd of strangers.
tired from the journey and the emotion of his strange reunion with America.
Strangely,
He was shy.
And at that moment,
He was fragile.
nervous,
I'm really nervous about being in Hollywood.
And then suddenly,
a man leans over his shoulder.
That's his old friend Groucho Marx.
the star of the Marx Brothers.
They haven't crossed paths for decades.
Chaplin says to Groucho Marx,
"Stay warm,
Groucho,
You're next.
That meant,
I believe,
Ah!
Stay alive and you'll get your Oscar too.
And he was right.
Groucho Marx would receive an honorary Oscar the following year.
Chaplin left as soon as the meal was over.
He spends the rest of the afternoon at his hotel.
Then comes the Oscars ceremony,
here,
at the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion in Los Angeles.
The inscription tells Charles Chaplin that the incalculable effect he had by making moving images,
This is the art form of this century.
He deserved that Oscar.
Of course.
Who else,
my God,
If it weren't for Chaplin?
The Americans finally gave him an Oscar.
After,
He should have won ten Oscars.
There was a standing ovation.
I was just below him.
And he was crying.
He was crying.
Everyone was actually crying.
The ovation was incredible.
She didn't stop.
One minute.
two minutes,
three minutes.
People were still standing.
They applauded.
they shouted.
And Chaplin remained standing.
After this incredible and seemingly endless ovation,
Everyone else sits down and he remains standing.
And then he gives a short speech.
My mother used to say, "But you're not allowed to cry."
to compliment them,
which he did immediately.
Oh,
You are wonderful.
Yes,
people.
Thank you.
It was the most moving moment imaginable.
All those crazy years,
Hollywood,
the holidays,
the films,
misfortunes,
all of that,
to arrive in 1972,
at that moment of grace.
Which was a little bit sad,
To be perfectly honest,
It was because he no longer had the face of Charlie Chaplin.
of the young Charlie Chaplin.
I don't know why he was betrayed by America.
because the Americans loved him.
They wanted him back.
Perhaps not the officials,
the FBI,
but the public,
Yes,
They loved him.
It was an incredible ceremony.
A question then arises.
Chaplin's emotion that evening,
Is she really who we think she is?
He is, of course, touched by this tribute.
But after 20 years of exile...
He hasn't forgotten anything.
As soon as he received his Oscar,
he told his wife,
"I want to go home,
I've had enough.
I want to go home.
Back to the continent.
But then why this injury?
How did she come about?
Until the end of his life,
Chaplin would remain in conflict with a certain segment of America.
How could the man who created so much,
invented,
which made the whole world laugh,
Could he have been driven out of the country that made him king?
The history of this dispute begins 60 years earlier.
when a young English actor,
Talented and ambitious...
Set out to conquer the new world.
In December 1912,
An English musical troupe is traveling across the United States towards New York.
The troupe of Londoner Fred Carnot,
the biggest promoter of comedy shows in England.
When we had a little success in England,
After touring English cities,
The real Eldorado was the United States.
For the past 6 years,
A promising young actor has joined the troupe.
He is 23 years old and is participating in the American tour for the second time.
When they started the American tour,
The initial reviews weren't very good.
Except that everyone was saying,
There is this man,
Chaplin.
That evening...
The New York public is about to discover a phenomenon.
In this new show,
Chaplin plays a very innovative character.
He does not appear on stage.
But amidst the spectators, something never seen before.
He was part of the audience and he played a drunk who starts to heckle the actors and disrupt the show.
He was a troublemaker and everyone laughed at him.
He made people laugh more than the others.
He kept falling off his seat.
He was truly the star of the show.
This little Englishman makes the public laugh so much that he ends up attracting the interest of major American critics.
After this performance,
This is what the very popular Variety magazine wrote.
Charles Chaplin is the trademark,
the lead actor.
Chaplin is typically English,
He's the kind of actor that American audiences will appreciate.
A few weeks later,
on tour in Philadelphia,
Chaplin receives a strange telegram.
from a New York law firm.
He is looking for someone named Chaffin.
If there is indeed a Chaffin in your company,
Tell him to contact the Kessel & Bowman law firm on Broadway.
The message comes from New York.
where one of her aunts lives.
Chaplin immediately thought of an inheritance.
He almost hoped that she was dead and that she would leave him something.
Therefore,
The young actor returns to New York.
to meet with the lawyers.
But she wasn't brought in because of an inheritance matter.
Kessel and Bowman have just invested in a new film company,
Kestone,
directed by the famous producer
Max Ennett.
He had heard of a certain Charles Chaplin and he thought he had potential.
The lawyers offered him a contract of $175 per week.
a fortune at the time.
That's three times more
than what he earns at Carnot's.
Financially,
It was an offer he couldn't refuse.
But Chaplin hesitated.
He believes he is a theatre man, not a cinema man.
He demands guarantees and negotiates a one-year contract.
He is then hired,
but he must nevertheless finish his tour with the Carnot troupe.
The last few months of performing are difficult.
The young actor is anxious about leaving this family.
That's where he honed his skills.
That's where he learned all his acts.
He perfected the art of mime.
In December 1913,
It's time to leave.
Chaplin bids farewell to the troupe and heads to California.
Upon his arrival in Los Angeles,
Chaplin sets off to explore the Keystone studios.
For the past two years,
The company is booming.
The filming sessions are proceeding in quick succession.
The excitement is constant.
Max Hedet's factory,
These are guys who make a film in two days.
if it's a one-day event.
The jokes,
They are quite basic,
They're cream pies,
It's the policeman versus the thief.
Chaplin never saw anything like it.
Very impressed.
He doesn't dare to introduce himself.
He was very anxious.
He drove past the Keystone studios several days in a row.
And he saw those crazy people running around everywhere.
So he left again.
Chaplin arrives in that world.
I know he's already had a revelation about cinema.
He finds it extraordinary.
But he doesn't know what role he really plays in it.
The producer then demands his presence.
And Chaplin came to take his first steps in cinema.
In this very first film...
He plays a cunning young journalist.
A start that was not very conclusive for Max Ennett.
The producer finds his new recruit too young.
He does not recognize the drunkard he had spotted within the Carnot troupe.
He made a lot of mistakes.
He did things that are done in English musicals in front of an audience.
but not something you do in front of cameras.
He seemed very likeable on screen.
His face,
its movements,
his mime.
But he needed a character.
So what do we do with this guy?
This is precisely the question that Max Sennett asks himself until the day he challenges Chaplin.
Sennett needs an extra,
So he asks his new recruit to urgently create a character.
by raiding the wardrobe of the other actors.
He tried on clothes and nothing really suited him.
Chaplin improvises and decides to mix the sizes.
Trousers that are too wide
a jacket that's too small.
As he did at Carnot's,
He adds a mustache to look older.
This is an emergency.
He didn't sit down at a table and sketch a suit.
No,
no,
he took,
There you go,
he saw that funny hat,
I'll take it too.
Therefore,
He quickly joined the set wearing this costume.
this hat,
this cane.
And this surprising approach.
Even if it had been created by accident,
This costume was the right one.
Chaplin enters the scene.
The team's reaction was immediate.
He was only supposed to be an extra.
He's all we see.
He's a Trump.
a tramp.
but with gestures,
the attitudes and sensitivities of a gentleman.
Actually,
Chaplin reprises the drunken persona that made him successful in the Carnot troupe.
But this new character has something unique about it,
a kind of natural poetry.
Under the watchful eye of his now enthusiastic producer,
Charlie Chaplin...
is being born.
Sennett then asked Chaplin to immediately test this clown character in another film.
The filming is completely improvised outdoors and without a script.
There was a fun event in Venice,
a children's car race.
Boys were racing each other in makeshift cars,
soapbox cars,
That sort of thing.
They had absolutely no idea what they were going to do here.
But Chaplin and his cameraman had an idea.
They went and sat down in the middle of the track.
And Charlie started clowning around until the police arrived and threw them out.
After a few minutes,
The magic works.
The public is no longer even interested in the race.
captivated by this strange agitator.
This is an exceptional document.
because the onlookers,
the spectators of the race,
They are also the first people in the world to have seen Chaplin's Little Tramp.
February 7, 1914,
for the first time,
Charlie Chaplin appears in movie theaters.
The success was immediate.
Without delay,
Keystone commissioned more films from Charlie Chaplin.
As filming progressed,
He is refining his character.
his attitude,
its story.
In this country where everyone dreams of becoming a Rockefeller,
He chose to portray a vagabond,
without money,
without family and without a past.
He is poor.
His oversized trousers meant he used to be fat.
but that he lost weight and was never able to regain it.
He is somewhat mocked by those who live in sedentary places.
this figure.
A free agent who belongs to no company,
to no clan,
who is always on the road.
He is a vagabond,
He is a victim.
From the outset,
The world has ostracized him.
And he goes,
thanks to his clever trick,
thanks to the way it moves,
He'll get through this.
The character must fight at every moment.
It is in a state of permanent crisis.
He needs to find his next meal.
He has to find the girl.
In a harsh world,
a world where the police prevent him from sleeping,
a world where others are bigger than him.
Each time,
It's David versus Goliath.
a universal theme.
What touches me,
It is the social perception he has of those around him.
who is extremely lucid,
extremely sharp,
and how he makes it both very funny and very touching.
The intentions are sincere.
We are entering into an agreement with Chaplin.
This shows how exaggerated the gestures are.
attitudes sometimes,
something that couldn't be done in cinema today,
But he can afford it.
Because it's sincere.
A vagabond enamored with adventure and freedom,
who likes women and alcohol,
an anti-hero who challenges established norms.
How could Chaplin have come up with the idea of ​​such a transgressive character for his time?
Simply by drawing on his childhood memories,
in England,
in his years of misery haunted by the ghost of a man he would have liked to know better.
Some say that
The cause was women.
and others say it was the father.
And on each of his visits,
Images from the past come back to him.
We are on Kennington Road.
in 1901.
Like all the children in the neighborhood,
Chaplin knew misery and poverty.
His parents separated a few months after his birth.
He lives with his mother Anna and doesn't see his father very often.
Charles Chaplin Senior,
a great musical singer.
Yet he lives just two streets away.
with another woman.
Chaplin,
for a short period,
remained living at home with his new partner.
And he often saw his father very drunk and very sad.
Chaplin Senior achieved fame.
Records have been produced under his name.
But ever since Charlie's mother left him,
He never managed to regain his former success.
And it's in the pubs of Kennington that he tries to forget all of this.
It was a tradition in the musical world.
All artists are...
They offered tours continuously.
After the show,
They would meet at the bar.
For them,
It was free.
just to encourage customers to drink.
Chaplin Senior was only 37 years old.
but he was already ravaged by alcohol.
Charlie will always remember the last time he met his father.
He was 12 years old.
It was in April 1901.
outside a pub.
A bottle in hand.
He was very shocked to see how swollen he was from the illness.
During this meeting,
They embraced, and for the first time,
His father kissed him.
That's the last memory he had of it.
Three weeks later,
Chaplin Senior collapses onto a table,
in a pub in Kennington,
victim of liver cirrhosis.
The death of his father caused him a terrible fear of what alcohol could lead to.
In fact, he has never drunk alcohol in his life.
He had learned all the attitudes of a drunkard by watching his father stagger and he drew a perfect imitation from it.
Chaplin would continually draw upon his childhood memories to transform the tragedy of London's forgotten people into a universal comedy.
As if Charlie Chaplin were born to bring justice to his unfortunate brothers,
to the bloodletting,
to the oppressed,
by bearing witness to their lives.
And indeed,
The character Charlie Chaplin continues to captivate the public.
In 1917,
three years after its creation,
Chaplin became Hollywood's most prominent movie star.
He has already directed more than 60 short films,
producers were exchanged twice.
He acts in and directs his own films.
To renegotiate its contracts,
He brought his half-brother out of obscurity,
Sidney.
Sidney was a brilliant businessman.
Charlie too,
but Sidney was even more so.
Charlie was so busy creating comedies that he didn't pay much attention to business.
He knew he was worth money,
that he needed to win some.
but didn't pay much attention to detail.
And that's where Sidney came in.
Sidney was very involved in his brother's publicity.
Finally,
he took care of everything,
In fact.
And that,
that's a very important element in Chaplin's approach.
Especially a family that hadn't had the opportunity to be together.
They really stuck together back then.
And in June 1917,
Sidney will be able to demonstrate the full extent of his talents.
Chaplin has just been contacted by a major New York company.
First National.
The tide has turned.
the little guy from Killington Road,
can become rich
very rich,
And he's not going to let the opportunity pass him by.
They wanted to commission 8 short films from Charlie.
SO,
They called him in Hollywood to see if they could do business together.
Charlie and Sidney are taking the train to New York.
and during the journey,
Chaplin will be able to measure for the first time the full extent of his popularity.
Chaplin traveled under his real name.
Charles Spencer.
He was traveling across the United States by train and there were many stops.
He was very surprised to see that at each stop,
There was a huge crowd.
And he thought,
There must be a celebrity on this train.
And then finally,
He realized that fame,
It was him.
He makes films,
He makes films.
And then all of a sudden,
He raises his head and realizes that it's an interplanetary star.
Everyone was talking about Charlie Chaplin.
And a strange phenomenon has appeared in the country.
It was called Chaplinitis,
Chaplin's madness.
This was the beginning of cinema.
There had never been stars like that before.
There is no place in the world where people don't know the character of Chaplin.
what he recounted,
the emotions he evoked.
This train journey has done its work.
Chaplin never imagined he would achieve such fame.
He now has a dream.
to become a millionaire.
For Chaplin, money was the lifeblood of the industry.
He has always known how to be independent.
That's truly its greatest strength.
very early.
Maturity,
beyond the artist's genius,
There is a businessman to target who realizes he needs to be independent.
Having arrived in New York,
Charlie and Sidney are waiting for their contact at the hotel.
To relax,
Charlie brought his violin.
But after this long journey...
If it lacks a little bit of...
patience.
Charlie played the violin very badly.
really very bad,
and his brother could no longer stand to hear him play the violin.
SO,
Since Charlie still wanted to play,
He asked her to go to the bathroom and closed the door.
When the representatives of the national force arrive,
Charlie stays in the bathroom and lets his brother negotiate.
He comes back after 15-20 minutes and says to Charlie,
"They don't accept your proposal."
They won't go beyond $500,000.
Charlie continued playing the violin and said to him,
" You know,
Sidney,
We were told we would get a million dollars.
You should go back there.
Sidney understands that the negotiation is only just beginning.
He returns to see his brother several times.
with new proposals,
in vain.
Sidney comes back and says
Charlie, this is their final offer.
They no longer want to negotiate.
That's $750,000.
Not one more.
Charlie replies
Tell them I'm an artist.
I know nothing about money.
But all I know,
I want a million dollars.
Ten minutes later,
He comes back and writes,
Charlie,
Throw away your violin.
You can buy yourself a cello,
You have your million dollars.
With his million dollars in his pocket,
Chaplin is now free to do what he wants in Hollywood.
He started by having his own studio built.
A studio that reflects his personality, with offices and decor inspired by the London of his childhood.
Obviously,
He missed England.
He had experienced many misfortunes there.
But he liked being English.
SO,
This British-style studio reminded him of his roots.
It was warmer for him.
That's why he had it done that way.
And in its new studios,
Chaplin recreates a family.
On camera,
his faithful Rolly Tostrow,
from whom he learned the art of filmmaking.
Rolly was my grandfather.
And he was Chaplin's cameraman for 38 years.
Rolly was his closest confidant.
He was helping him,
Strictly speaking,
to make his films.
He really chooses who he's going to work with.
And that's where a real period begins.
It really is,
He is at the height of his power.
From now on, Chaplin is the sole master of the ship.
He's acting,
directs the other actors,
He shoots and edits his own films.
When he lacks inspiration,
The entire machine stops.
When an idea arises,
everyone must be on high alert.
He enjoyed tremendous freedom thanks to his success.
thanks to his company and the money he earned.
So for him,
It wasn't about making money.
It was about doing high-quality things.
Whatever the cost.
Charlie Chaplin's films enjoyed enormous popular success.
Yet,
The filmmaker is starting to have detractors.
In the eyes of a certain segment of America,
Chaplin remains an outsider.
who made his fortune here
but who refuses to take American citizenship.
Worse,
He uses his character to mock the system.
A committee was formed in America to say that it was too violent.
vulgar.
He was showing off too much of his bourgeois side.
A bit too anarchistic.
and that he needed to calm down.
He criticized people who had a lot of money.
etc.
and touched on aspects of society that no one had touched before.
In humor,
as soon as we gather together and as soon as it starts to make noise,
Then things started to get a little tense.
Characters like Chaplin are characters who have also been disturbing.
In Washington,
One man in particular already has Chaplin in his sights.
His name is Jay Edgar Hoover.
He is only 21 years old and has just been hired by the Department of Justice to monitor foreign nationals.
A function that Chaplin recently ridiculed in his film The Immigrant.
Hoover cannot stand it and he begins to take an interest in Chaplin's case.
The fact that he did not want to take American citizenship,
This creates suspicion.
That is to say, he cannot be a good American since he is not even American.
So right away,
He becomes a target for Hoover because he is someone who is absolutely not a conformist.
And the nonconformists,
like Chaplin,
This is the beginning of subversion for Hoover.
Hoover is not yet the powerful head of the FBI.
The Federal Bureau of Investigation would not be created until 7 years later.
But he's already keeping an eye on Chaplin.
And he soon discovers that he has a weakness.
In 1918,
The new fortunes of cinema are settling in the hills of Beverly Hills.
where they organize decadent parties.
It contains alcohol,
drugs...
and young actresses.
Chaplin is of course a prominent member of what is known as the Hollywood colony.
Many of his friends are lost in the party.
He was very good at entertaining people.
to amuse them,
to make them laugh.
He had all that.
But I think he never did that.
He never got lost in that.
For him,
no alcohol,
no drugs.
On the other hand...
He likes women,
and above all
very young women.
At one of his parties,
He meets Mildred Harris.
It was at Sam Goldwyn's house.
at whose house he used to play poker.
She was as short as he was.
and he liked girls his own height,
if you know what I mean.
Mildred Harris dreams of becoming an actress.
She was only 16 years old at the time.
Chaplin falls under her spell.
But the idyll will be brief.
He thought Mildred Harris was very pretty.
But Chaplin himself said that she wasn't very intelligent.
He thought they were incompatible.
But Mildred is more cunning than she appears.
She has no intention of letting Hollywood's best catch slip away.
A few weeks after they met,
She tells him that she is pregnant.
Chaplin gets scared.
Mildred is a minor.
He risks going to prison.
He is forced to marry her.
Mildred Harris,
like many young girls in Hollywood,
he was thinking about his career.
And becoming Mrs. Chaplin could certainly have helped her.
So she made him believe she was pregnant.
But in reality, she wasn't.
They got married and she became pregnant after the wedding.
Chaplin fell into the trap.
Married to a woman he doesn't love,
He enters a period of artistic stagnation.
It is certain that his marriage to Mildred Harris was a kind of creative block.
He was starting to make films.
He abandoned them.
To escape this forced marriage and rediscover his love of cinema,
in January 1919,
Chaplin launches United Artists,
a new film company founded with his two best friends.
The acting couple Douglas Fairbank and Mary Pickford.
It was Douglas and Mary who convinced him to come and live near them.
Charlie,
Douglas and Mary were like brother and sister.
They loved each other that much.
On the day of the signing,
as per usual,
Chaplin makes people laugh and saves appearances.
But the drama he is experiencing at home is only getting worse.
Norman,
the child Mildred is carrying,
has a malformation.
He died three days after his birth.
Obviously,
It was a tough blow for Chaplin.
But it's strange because,
From that moment on,
He had the idea of ​​making a film with a child.
At 30 years old,
devastated by the loss of his first child and the failure of his marriage,
Chaplin then went back to work to extract one of his greatest masterpieces from his personal tragedy.
Four days after the death of his son,
Chaplin auditioned young boys at the studio.
Initially,
He was looking for children for one of his productions.
"Charlot Picnic".
But during the casting process,
A boy will move him so much that he hires him on the spot.
His name is Jackie Coogan.
He was saying something about Jackie Coogan.
I don't know why,
But every time I see that boy,
I feel like crying.
A few days later...
Bankers and foreign investors are visiting the studios.
It has been months since Chaplin produced a film.
The atmosphere is heavy,
But Jackie Coogan's company will help to reassure the financiers.
They put on his Chaplin uniform.
They are very happy.
They play with the kid.
Jackie Coogan,
of which they have absolutely no idea what he will do with it.
and to amuse the bankers.
He said,
Jackie is so malleable that when I show her something,
He manages to do it exactly as I show him.
He does it again and again without losing spontaneity or emotion.
He truly felt that he had found the perfect actor in Jackie Coogan.
Jackie reassured investors,
but above all he inspired Chaplin.
He then had the idea for his first feature film,
in which Charlie Chaplin would adopt a child.
He will simply call him the Kid.
Therefore,
A wound is reopening.
A figure from the past reappears.
His mother's,
Anna.
And this tragedy of abandonment that they experienced side by side,
Mother and son.
At the end of the
19th century,
Anna Chaplin is a musical artist.
She is raising her two sons alone.
Charlie and Sidney.
Since his divorce from Charles Chaplin Senior,
All she has to offer her sons is the misery of Kennington Road.
Even when she was at rock bottom,
She taught them a love of theatre and creativity.
She told them biblical stories,
entertained them with anecdotes from musicals,
And he said she was a wonderful imitator.
But Anna is unwell.
She hasn't worked for a long time.
She spends entire days at home calling out to people in the street.
Actually,
She is slowly descending into madness.
He watched her gradually become depressed and psychotic.
She was looking out the window; what she was saying made no sense.
He witnessed all of that.
It broke his heart.
In 1898,
Anna is interned at the Canhille asylum.
Doctors are alarmed.
The case is very serious.
His mental illness was a consequence of a venereal disease.
more specifically syphilis.
She was believed to have suffered from stage 3 syphilis.
The doctors said that this was the cause of his madness because at level 3,
It is the nervous system that is affected.
Charlie will never know how his mother contracted this disease.
Anna was a fickle woman who loved men.
He spent several months at the orphanage until he returned home.
But a few years later,
She's having a terrible relapse.
A day,
Children came to tell him,
Your mother has gone crazy.
She is in the street and she is distributing pieces of coal to passers-by.
He had to go and get her to take her to the hospice.
then to the asylum.
And this time,
Charlie will have to take her back to the asylum himself.
He is now 14 years old.
lives alone with her.
His brother Sidney joined the navy.
The image of a 14-year-old boy having to take his poor, mentally ill mother to the hospital,
leave her there,
then leave alone.
It's a terrible image we have of Chaplin's life at that time.
From this day forward,
Anna will never leave the psychiatric hospital again.
Charlie finds himself completely alone.
but he refuses to return to the orphanage.
The London orphanage of that time,
It was very, very hard.
It was like being in prison.
So all of this deeply traumatized him.
And he was very proud,
He was left alone.
People offered him help,
He said no.
How's it going.
For several months,
Charlie survives by working here and there.
Sometimes,
He is forced to sleep in the street.
The situation continued until his brother Sidney,
back in England,
eventually find him.
When Sidney returned from South Africa,
He took Charlie under his wing.
He helped him financially until he found him a job in the theatre.
Effective from this day forward,
The two brothers will never leave each other's side again.
All the memories of that difficult childhood,
his feeling of abandonment,
Chaplin instilled them in the kid.
He manages to transcend his grief.
But a new challenge awaits him.
As filming draws to a close,
His wife Mildred launches an attack.
She accuses him in the press of having deserted the marital home.
I didn't see Mr.
Chaplin for the past two weeks,
And I haven't lived with him for months.
I conclude that he has left me.
During this time,
His lawyers are launching divorce proceedings and planning to ruin the filmmaker.
Mrs. Chaplin asks the court to freeze the funds committed by Mr.
Chaplin in several films.
Funds estimated at over $500,000.
In other words,
The lawyers are demanding the kid's tapes.
But Chaplin has no intention of letting his film be stolen.
In the middle of the night,
He wakes up his entire team.
Grandfather says that he came to his house,
knocked on the door and said...
Come to the studio,
includes the films,
We have to leave.
He had to take the film negatives to Salt Lake City.
then in New Jersey.
He wanted to escape the bailiffs who were seeking to reclaim them as joint property.
They could have taken everything from him and he was very afraid of that.
For weeks,
He travels across the United States from hotel to hotel, always one step ahead of the bailiffs.
It was a kind of Chaplin film that was unfolding in parallel.
He walked through hotel lobbies dressed as a woman so that no one would recognize him.
He was going to hide in the desert with his reels of film.
He's the character from those movies,
That is to say, the whole world is turning against him.
Well, despite its small size,
He's getting a real beating.
But the guy just keeps going.
Eventually,
This whole story comes to an end after a long legal and media battle.
The divorce was finalized in November 1920.
Mildred Harris receives $200,000 and half of Chaplin's estate.
In return,
He was able to save his film.
The kit was released in theaters two months later.
His success surpassed anything Chaplin had experienced before.
The reviews are said to be scathing and crowds are flocking to all the cinemas.
The film has been sold in 50 countries.
This is a new record.
That's his greatest achievement.
The way he manages to make you laugh and cry at the same time.
For the first time,
There are some very, very dramatic scenes in The Kid.
In particular, at one point Daz goes to get the child.
We see Jackie Coogan stretching his arms out like this.
We see Chaplin taking them,
The violins are screaming from all sides,
He continues across the rooftops.
the car,
He even goes so far as to get into a fight with someone.
very strong elements that did not exist before in Chaplin's work,
He enters a truly dramatic world.
It was the first film in which he had really drawn on his childhood memories.
But the most moving thing,
It was because he had just lost his child.
A few
weeks after the release of The Kid,
Chaplin experiences another upheaval in his life.
His mother,
Anna,
arrives in the United States.
After more than ten years of separation,
He decided to bring her to Hollywood.
One of her assistants went to pick her up at the port of New York,
But the reunion looks set to be complicated.
She seemed really well and she went to the immigration office.
When the agent asked her, "Are you Charles Chaplin's mother?"
She replied, "Yes,
And you,
you are Jesus Christ.”
It could have gone badly,
But no,
and she was able to go live in California.
Charlie found him a small house north of Hollywood.
She would spend the last eight years of her life there.
Anna receives many visitors.
but rarely his son.
There was a couple who took care of her.
All she wanted,
She had it.
But it was very depressing for him to go see her.
What stands out most to me,
I believe,
It was about being confronted with his mother's madness.
The mother he had loved,
the mother of his memories,
was beautiful
talented,
full of vitality.
The woman she had become was psychotic.
obese,
old before her time,
a character who is both sad and tragic.
His grandmother and mother ended up in psychiatric institutions.
And I think he also had a slight fear of one day going crazy.
This is Chaplin's great tragedy,
the one he will try to exorcise in his love life.
This happy memory of a young and beautiful mother,
He will relentlessly search for him in his romantic conquests.
This explains a little why he was attracted to young girls.
Not out of an obsession with young girls,
but above all out of fear of old age.
And three years after his divorce from Mildred Harris,
Chaplin falls in love again.
In love once again,
of a teenage girl.
With Lockheed,
Chaplin developed a taste for feature films.
In 1924,
He is embarking on a monumental project.
The Street and Verlore.
Natural settings,
over 600 extras and a budget of $2 million,
It's the most expensive film of the year.
They had hired a group of bums in Sacramento and brought them in by train to film the opening scene.
It was quite difficult,
in the middle of all this snow,
trying to control the holds and everything that was happening.
Charlie Chaplin also takes on a new dimension in this film.
A more philosophical dimension.
Chaplin returns to his major themes.
love,
hunger,
poverty and lack of gain.
Some scenes will become iconic.
But the filming will once again be disrupted by Chaplin's private life.
That young actress behind him...
Her name is Lita Gray.
She is 15 years old.
At the start of filming,
She plays the lead role.
Chaplin had met her during the casting of The Kid,
three years earlier.
Charlie was looking for a pretty girl for the Kid.
She introduced herself,
She was wearing her mother's heels.
She had put her hair up and she went through the audition.
Chaplin liked her very much.
According to Lita,
He supposedly created that dream sequence in The Kid solely to offer him the character of the angel.
In this surreal and premonitory sequence,
Charlie Chaplin had to resist the angel of temptation.
portrayed by the young Lita Gray,
then only aged
12 years old.
None of Chaplin's associates thought she was particularly photogenic or talented.
But she was engaged.
because Chaplin was enthusiastic and no one opposed his enthusiasm.
Three years later,
Chaplin therefore hired him again for the gold rush.
But they have an affair during filming.
and the girl becomes pregnant.
She then has to give up her role.
Chaplin suggested that she have an abortion.
But Lita's family said no.
and they insisted that they get married.
The marriage was celebrated in Mexico and made official in the press on November 26, 1924.
For the second time,
Chaplin has just married a teenage girl to avoid prison.
He told her immediately,
I have no intention of being a husband to you.
I will be there for social reasons.
But there will be nothing else.
Charlie will, however, have two children with Lita.
Charles Junior,
then Sidney.
But that doesn't change anything.
The young woman feels neglected.
then at 18 years old,
She leaves the marital home and files for divorce.
It was worse than her first divorce.
They fought it out in the press with sensational headlines.
In the press,
Lita Gray paints a scathing portrait of the father of her children.
Further tarnishing Chaplin's image.
Mrs. Chaplin states that the actor threatened her twice with a revolver and suggested she commit suicide.
It is said that her hair turned white around the time of her divorce from Lita Gray.
almost overnight.
It's still amazing to see that Charlie Chaplin,
who observed human nature so well,
was unable to see his own flaws.
Meanwhile in Washington,
his worst enemy,
J.
Edgar Hoover,
has just taken up his duties as head of the FBI.
His first target,
Hollywood.
Accused by the leagues of corrupting America,
He is determined to restore order and morality there.
What bothers him about Hollywood,
It's amplified tenfold by Chaplin.
That is to say, there is a space for freedom in Hollywood,
whether at the political level or at the level of morals.
that it doesn't exist anywhere else in American society.
What Hoover deeply disliked about Chaplin,
That's his freedom.
But the filmmaker does not yet sense this growing threat.
because for the moment,
He has other concerns.
In the late 1920s,
Everything is falling apart in Hollywood.
The 1929 financial crisis shook the American economy and did not spare the film industry.
Studios are closing one after another.
Chaplin received better advice.
He had time to secure his fortune.
But there is something else that worries him.
The arrival of a technological revolution,
talking pictures.
Buster Keaton,
L'Oréal and Hardy,
all the stars of his generation,
have fallen into oblivion.
So what will Charlie Chaplin do in the face of this major upheaval?
He, who has always been at the forefront,
at the forefront of modernity,
persists in believing in the future of mature cinema.
In the late 1920s,
Concern is growing at the Chaplin studio.
The return of theaters is not good.
All the recent silent films have not been successful.
During depression,
Things were tough,
Many studios had closed.
Chaplin had just divorced Lita Gray,
So he had a lot of money problems.
Chaplin felt the pressure mounting from all sides.
This, incidentally, inspired a scene in his new film.
the circus.
For the first time,
Chaplin no longer fills theaters.
The circus was his first commercial failure.
Charlie is worried about what will happen next.
A talking film
a silent film,
What does my future hold?
Nobody knew what was going to happen.
It was the beginning of the end for everyone.
They were devastated.
From now on,
Everything had changed for them.
Even his own brother,
Sidney,
usually so optimistic,
feels the wind changing.
They have just narrowly escaped the stock market crash.
With everything they've earned in the last 15 years,
They can live very comfortably until the end of their days.
Sidney then suggests they set sail.
He told Charlie,
It's good,
We've done enough.
We stop.
And Charlie said,
not me.
When his brother told him,
The visiting room is arriving.
We stop everything.
We have enough.
etc.
He said,
no,
I still have things to say.
I'll say it like that because that's how I know how to do it.
And Sidney said,
I'm stopping.
And he did it.
Sidney returns to Europe to live out his days happily.
Charlie thus finds himself alone to face the end of the silent era.
He made so many beautiful silent films,
all great successes.
And then comes a technological revolution that he doesn't quite know how to handle.
So he was cautious about talking films.
Chaplin had another problem with the arrival of talking pictures.
He hates his own voice.
Can he continue to be Charlie Chaplin and speak at the same time?
Because Charlie doesn't speak.
He expresses himself with his face,
with his way of being,
with his playing style,
with his body.
Chaplin had a big problem and he solved it.
simply by not speaking.
It's decided,
Chaplin will not succumb to the allure of modernity.
For him,
Talking pictures are just a passing fad.
His new film,
City Lights,
will be mute.
The first one took place in New York in January 1931.
All of Hollywood traveled across the United States to discover the new Chaplin.
The filmmaker invited another genius of his century,
his new friend,
Professor Albert Einstein.
He was afraid that no one would come to see the film because no silent film had been released for years.
The film is a love story between Charlie Chaplin and a little flower girl who has lost her sight.
A poetic work,
moving.
and without any dialogue.
In the end,
It became the third biggest success of the year.
Life magazine stated
"The mute,
if Chaplin directs,
It's still gold.
He provides the essential demonstration that one can remain what one wants to be.
whatever the situation.
I think everyone needs to have people remind us of that from time to time.
Chaplin is once again making headlines.
But this time, it's for his art.
A success that, however, does not reassure him.
Alone,
tired and worried about the future of cinema,
He needs to take a step back.
He wants to escape the gloom and doom in Hollywood.
So what is he going to do?
How can we avoid being perceived as an anachronism?
like a star from a bygone era,
Completely off the mark?
In February 1931,
He will leave the United States and California to promote city lights in Europe.
He has no idea yet how much this trip will change his worldview and give his art a second youth.
First stop,
England.
Chaplin arrives in his hometown by train and finds his smile again.
The prodigal son has returned.
He enjoyed being appreciated by the people of the countries he visited.
but he also liked being able to be received there as a prominent figure who could engage in dialogue with heads of state,
intellectuals,
other artists.
In London,
Winston Churchill,
future Prime Minister
asks to meet him.
Mahatma Gandhi,
came to negotiate India's independence with England,
is also curious to see it.
By positioning itself alongside the greats of the 20th century,
He himself became a great figure of the 20th century.
But beyond the popular jubilation and enthusiasm for his films,
Chaplin realizes that the Great Depression has spread beyond the borders of America.
Throughout Europe,
People suffer and great nations retreat into themselves.
He had become very aware of the global situation.
And what he saw,
The global situation was spiraling out of control.
These were the dangers of nationalism.
In March 1931,
Chaplin arrives in Germany.
And for the first time, he himself will be the target of this prevailing nationalism.
In Berlin,
The people gave him a triumphant welcome.
But the Nazi press unleashed a torrent of attacks against him.
Because he is a friend of Albert Einstein,
He is said to be Jewish.
"Does he leave the aforementioned lady to a sub-Gewandereux?"
a tot-feind.
In a dictionary they compiled to list a number of Jewish figures,
They include Chaplin.
Charlie Chaplin.
This wiggling little Jew,
boring and repugnant has become a myth of our time for Jewish families.
That era is over.
Upon discovering this text and its accompanying photo in this list of men to be eliminated,
Chaplin is in shock,
but he decides to leave his origins shrouded in doubt.
He is not Jewish.
but he will never try to deny it.
He always said that denying being Jewish would be playing into the hands of anti-Semites.
But the trip to Berlin holds another surprise for him.
The press also mentions a striking resemblance.
a strange coincidence of dates.
with one of the rising figures of the nationalist right.
When Chaplin arrived in Germany,
There are small cartoon drawings that start immediately,
even before Hitler seized power,
comparing the two,
the character of Charlot or the personality of Chaplin,
And
Adolf Hitler.
They were born almost on the same day,
the same year,
in 1889.
They had the same silhouette,
the same moustache.
There were newspapers that said Hitler got the idea for the moustache from Chaplin.
And that made him very angry.
Upon his return to the United States,
Chaplin keeps thinking about all of this.
He is no longer the same man.
At 43 years old,
He no longer just wants to make people laugh.
But he understands that his films can also raise awareness.
He witnessed the devastating effects of depression on nations.
SO,
His first target?
It will be capitalism.
In
In 1936, he donned his Charlie Chaplin costume once again for a satire of the industrial world.
Modern times,
It's a film that denounces excessive consumerism.
You don't see it as a light comedy,
but like a true social film.
And at the same time,
It's very funny.
It is a denunciation of everything that is happening today.
The world is doomed.
profit,
time,
money,
etc.
It's beautifully done and then we finally have Paulette Godard.
Paulette
Godard, Charlie Chaplin's new partner.
A 21-year-old actress whom he met upon her return from Europe,
He gave her the lead female role.
After a childhood quite similar to his own,
separation,
abandonment,
So there was a kind of compassion and identification between them.
This is his last silent film.
It's very moving to see that he found love along the way.
Moreover, for the first time, he is no longer going alone.
But this is not the love story that the public will remember from modern times.
Many people don't understand why Chaplin wanted to give a political dimension to his films.
The reception in the dining room was mixed.
However, this is only a first attempt.
because he is already writing a new pamphlet.
Adolf Hitler seized power in Germany,
And while no one in Hollywood seems to be reacting,
He intends to make a lasting impression.
He will, in a way, settle his score with this evil twin.
To portray his dictator,
Chaplin drew inspiration from a series of photos in which Hitler practiced striking poses.
Hitler took lessons with a teacher who taught him how to pose.
to learn to express oneself.
Chaplin immediately saw the strings behind what we might call Adolf Hitler's aura.
He,
he saw the puppet,
What?
He couldn't have imagined the horror that was about to unfold.
Of course,
but he saw the puppet.
So it was a source of inspiration.
A madman like that.
For the first time,
Chaplin wrote a screenplay with dialogue.
He devoted two whole years to it.
He resigned himself to abandoning the art of silent film.
out of necessity.
Only because he wanted speeches in it.
Speeches like those a politician would make.
In September 1939...
Chaplin began filming The Great Dictator in a very tense atmosphere.
His brother Sidney,
passing through,
turns his images in color.
At the same time,
The situation is worsening in Europe.
England and France have just declared war on Germany.
The United States refuses to take part in this war.
And Chaplin's project is causing a stir.
In particular J.
Edgar Hoover,
The head of the FBI became the most powerful man in America.
Hoover was like many American leaders of the time,
In other words, he viewed it rather favorably.
to begin with,
I think,
the rise of fascism in Germany,
for the simple reason that it is the alternative to communism.
SO,
Tell the Jews in Hollywood to stop exasperating the Germans.
This is not the right time.
Hitler,
you know,
He was very successful at the beginning.
So he's a kind of hero for many people too.
Chaplin was subjected to political and financial pressures.
But it doesn't bend.
On the contrary,
He's regained the energy of his early days.
He works day and night.
Repeat each take dozens of times.
The filming lasts more than 7 months.
Charlie was a workaholic.
It was not uncommon to stay 16 or 18 hours straight during filming.
And then come back the next day to start all over again.
Chaplin wants to be precise.
Nazi propaganda films inspired his set designs.
his costumes.
More than ever,
He wants to make this film a success.
Aware that the stakes this time are not just cinematic.
chart.
His demands on his team and on himself are limitless.
He's becoming this madman.
He becomes this tyrant.
He becomes this dictator,
but with the little thing,
the small gesture that changes everything.
On October 15, 1940,
The film is being screened in New York as a world premiere.
But then again...
Chaplin's political intent is not understood.
In the final scene,
Chaplin abandons his comedian's persona for a very committed personal speech.
You are not machines,
You are not cattle.
You are men!
You have love for humanity in your hearts.
When Chaplin's fame overshadows his character,
when Chaplin stopped playing the Tramp,
when he becomes a politically engaged man who gives speeches,
This is becoming problematic.
because he is becoming a very polarizing figure in America.
Let's do it for a world of reason!
A world where science and progress will lead to the joy of all mankind.
Soldiers,
in the name of democracy,
Let us all unite!
The film has indeed been nominated for five Oscars,
but few perceive its visionary aspect.
Yet,
in 1940,
Hitler has already begun his destructive project.
He had understood how to talk to people,
how to tell them about the world.
What he showed there was somewhat prophetic.
what was going to happen with the Jews.
He was the only one in Hollywood who released a film like that.
He said that if he had known about the extermination camps,
He could never have made a comedy out of it.
After the war,
It will be discovered that Hitler watched the dictator.
Nazi archives reveal the order for a copy of the film.
If the Nazi elite had one quality,
It's because she loved the cinema.
And even during the war,
The Nazis found ways to obtain English and American films through neutral countries.
The filmmaker has once again put a lot of himself into this film.
Starting with his relationship,
Paulette Godard left him during 1941 and divorced a year later.
They hadn't seen each other for months.
Those who collaborated with Chaplin know that he was totally absorbed in his work.
And of course,
His wives did not understand why he was completely neglecting them.
His entire mind was focused on his work.
Paulette Godard,
Magnificent.
I think it was...
With my mother,
It was also the end of his life.
He had a tremendous love affair with her.
This relationship truly humanized Chaplin.
That prepared him for Ouna.
Because two years later,
at 54 years old,
Chaplin makes a new acquaintance.
Ouna O'Neill,
the daughter of Nobel laureate Eugene O'Neill,
a 17-year-old aspiring actress who was going through her first auditions at the time.
When he met this other teenage girl,
Everyone around him was very anxious.
Everyone who knew about their romance believed it was still related to his attraction to young girls.
After all,
He was in his fifties and she was barely out of adolescence.
It could only have been his obsessive sexual fantasy.
But in reality,
It became his greatest love story.
They were passionately in love.
And he, who was a soft touch,
who collected women,
It was truly an extraordinary romance.
Chaplin married Una a few months after they met.
But the beginning of this mayor's term is marred by a new sex scandal.
The final straw.
June 4, 1943,
Joan Barry,
23 years old,
accuses Charlie Chaplin of being the father of her child.
He was indeed impregnated by a man who then killed him.
He had an affair with her,
one year before meeting Ouna.
But finding the young woman unstable,
He had preferred to break up quickly.
The whole story fell apart when Chaplin left her.
That's when she started causing a lot of problems.
Some time after their separation,
Joan Barry breaks into Chaplin's home in the middle of the night.
His son,
Sidney,
is present that evening.
He goes upstairs and sees his father looking worried.
He told him, "Dad,
"Can I come see you?"
And his father replied curtly, "No,
Not now " .
And then,
He sees Joan Barry in her father's room with a gun in her hands.
Joan Barry will be arrested twice for harassment.
Chaplin thought this matter was buried until this paternity suit was filed.
These accusations come at the same time as the official announcement of his marriage to Una.
For many Americans,
That's too much.
Chaplin's attraction to young women is no longer tolerable.
The American Legion,
Catholic veterans,
all feminist groups,
I think they didn't really like this image of disgusting old men living with young women.
For a segment of the population,
He was nothing more than an aging womanizer.
The John Barry case,
Many people turned their backs on him because of that.
And at the same time,
He marries Una O'Neill,
an 18-year-old girl when he is more than 5 years old.
In Washington,
A man rubs his hands together.
For over 20 years,
J.
Edgar Hoover is waiting for Chaplin's first misstep to bring him down.
His file has grown thicker over the years,
But he hasn't found anything illegal yet.
So this John Barry affair,
Hoover will take care of it personally.
What's fascinating,
This is how the FBI staged everything.
John Berry did not want to file a complaint.
J.
Edgar Hoover and essentially the entire American right wing used his story to demonize Chaplin.
And the FBI realized that it could initiate numerous proceedings.
February 15, 1944,
Chaplin appears in court for the acknowledgment of Caroline's paternity.
John Berry's daughter.
Chaplin's lawyer presents the results of a blood test that proves he is not the father.
But the FBI is in control of the situation.
That's huge.
The reason is that it was the FBI itself that appointed the judge.
And so,
The blood tests were rejected.
Chaplin is found guilty.
And he is ordered to pay alimony to John Barry's daughter until she turns 21.
But for Hoover,
That is not enough.
The head of the FBI then launched another procedure.
He found a very old federal law that prohibits a man from taking a woman on a trip.
for immoral purposes,
the manact.
Because he took John Barry on vacation to New York,
Chaplin risks
23 years in prison.
The prosecutor was horrible to him.
by portraying him as a sexual predator,
like a monster.
They photographed him while they were taking his fingerprints.
This photo appears in numerous newspapers.
Everything is being used to make him appear guilty.
But the jurors are not fooled.
On April 4, 1944,
They acquit Chaplin.
Yet,
Hoover doesn't let go of his prey.
And part of the conservative press remains in the pay of the FBI.
They spent their time giving small pieces of information to journalists who had rallied to their cause.
like Hedda Hopper,
which was definitely on the right.
Hedda Hopper,
who wrote for the tabloids at the time,
She's the one who started the rumors.
Feminist leagues are collecting signatures for petitions across the country.
They hope for Chaplin's deportation on grounds of moral turpitude.
Immigration services have informed me that they are investigating all aspects of his presence here.
An article signed
"Eda Hopper",
but which seems clearly dictated by Hoover.
The term "deportation"
is a term that is taken up by Hoover.
Besides,
He very often threatens people with deportation.
We know what deportation means.
The symbol is terrifying.
Chaplin is under attack from all sides.
But instead of keeping a low profile,
He responds with provocation.
With a new film,
Mr. Verdoux.
In it, he plays a woman-killer inspired by the French serial killer.
Landru.
Once again,
He found it amusing.
by playing Landru,
the French bluebeard who married wealthy widows and murdered them.
As a mask artist,
Doesn't the world encourage it?
Isn't this building weapons of destruction for the sole purpose of disguise?
Isn't that extinguishing women and children into tiny pieces?
It's more Chaplin.
What?
The little vagabond allowed him to get away with all sorts of things.
As soon as he leaves him,
He becomes more like everyone else.
One could say,
Oh,
Mr.
Verdoux,
What an excellent film.
But is this really reasonable for a man who has just come through a difficult paternity suit and who has a whole host of problems with women?
To play a Bluebeard who kills his wives for their money?
I'm going to lose my mind.
Nevertheless,
leaving behind this noise of earthly existence,
I have to say that I will see you all very soon.
The attack was clumsy and the result catastrophic for Chaplin.
The film was a commercial failure.
censored and banned in several states.
It was an organized boycott.
It was the beginning of the Cold War and there was a crusade against communism in the United States.
This was the missing piece for Hoover to deliver the fatal blow.
At the end of the 1940s,
The hunt for communists has just been officially launched by Senator McCarthy.
In this climate of paranoia and inquisition,
Chaplin's work then takes on a completely different meaning.
He had spoken out against what he saw as the excesses of industrial capitalism in modern times.
Hoover is looking for,
He searches and eventually finds a record of a speech in which Chaplin clearly supports the Russians.
1942.
He was asked to replace the Soviet ambassador in San Francisco at a large gathering in
1942. The goal was to push the government to open a second front.
He began his speech by saying to the audience
"comrades".
This moment,
when he said "comrades",
He was bound to be criticized.
Hoover thinks he's onto something.
Chaplin is being bugged,
His entourage is also being questioned.
" THE
The FBI came to see Sam Goldwyn and asked him if Chaplin was a communist.
He replied
"Charlie, a communist?"
He's the only true capitalist I know!
It was ridiculous.
Obviously,
He was closer to socialism.
from the left,
like many artists.
But he was not a communist at all.
Absolutely not.
Nothing, therefore, confirms a communist commitment.
But despite the lack of evidence,
All these years of anti-Chaplin propaganda are beginning to bear fruit.
In 1950,
in the United States,
We don't talk about these films anymore.
Forget the genius of the 7th art.
For Puritan America,
Chaplin is now nothing more than an old man with dangerous political ideas.
He was accused of being a communist.
And if you go to see a communist,
It means you're a supporter.
Otherwise, you yourself are a communist.
So it was the worst accusation in America.
He senses that a kind of mistrust and rejection is beginning to manifest itself.
All of Hollywood found him a bit tiresome.
He became persona non grata and no one came to visit him anymore.
So Chaplin gradually cut himself off from the world.
He spends his days in his villa and seeks comfort from his family.
his wife Ouna and their children.
A day,
We were walking towards the tennis court,
Just the two of them.
We talked about everything and nothing,
and at one point he told me
"I never knew what love was until I met this woman."
It just came out like that.
Very impressive.
She was like a surrogate mother to him.
his sister.
In addition,
Ouna somewhat corresponded to his ideal of a slightly fragile woman,
erased at the same time with a great deal of character.
But here's the thing,
It was a complete and mutual idyll.
Lover,
but withdrawn into himself,
in the melancholy of a bygone glory.
Chaplin would then create his final masterpiece,
The Footlights,
the story of a fallen musical artist,
his most autobiographical film.
For the first time,
He reunites the alcoholic artist with the young and beautiful dancer,
which obviously symbolizes the relationship of his own parents.
But her imagination transforms it into a love relationship.
happy and generous.
He entrusted the female role to Claire Bloom.
a young actress chosen for her resemblance to the two women in his life,
his mother and Una.
At that time,
One and I,
We were very similar.
And during the filming of the movie,
We were often mistaken for each other.
Chaplin wants to bring his story together.
his family,
to bring their lives together,
his children Geraldine,
Michael...
And Josephine even makes an appearance.
I wanted to tell everyone at school,
But I made films.
It's like following in your father's footsteps.
There's something archetypal about it that really made it a magical moment for me.
And in the role of the young suitor,
We also find Sidney,
the second son born from his marriage to Lita Gray.
Finally,
He chose the London of his childhood as the setting for his story.
reconstructed exactly as it was.
In one film,
Chaplin reviews all the major themes of his life.
It's a wonderful exploration of her feelings.
from his family,
feelings from his family
of its history,
of what he remembers of London.
And not always good times.
It's a very,
very rich.
A final film, a testament to his life.
almost prophetic,
He doesn't yet know that this will be the last one filmed in the United States.
In September 1952,
Chaplin sets sail for England.
This is the first planned stop on a long promotional tour in Europe for Limelight.
Because the film was set in London and things were going badly in the United States,
The first one was supposed to take place in London.
He knows that the FBI is watching him and that the IRS is looking for him.
So, out of fear of not being able to leave,
He did not announce the date of his departure.
And he boards the Queen Elizabeth in anonymity.
His wife and children are already on board.
He remained hidden in his cabin until the ship left the port.
But in Washington,
Hoover has no intention of detaining him.
On the contrary,
informed of his departure,
He's going to set a trap for him.
On the second day at sea,
Chaplin receives a message from immigration services.
His visa to return to the United States has just been refused.
Charlie was not officially banned,
He couldn't stop her from coming back.
But they created a situation where if he wanted a new visa,
He had to start all the official procedures again.
Hoover's trap is simple.
To obtain this visa,
Chaplin will have to undergo questioning by the FBI.
If he refuses,
He cannot come back.
If he accepts,
He will once again have to expose his private life.
in broad daylight.
During his absence,
They interviewed all the women who had had sexual relations with him.
with the aim of attacking his moral life.
They hoped he would come back and contradict himself.
in order to be able to indict him.
But he wasn't stupid enough for that.
The Queen Elizabeth arrives in England on September 23rd.
He presents himself to the English people as a good family man.
To begin with,
The triumphant welcome made him forget his American dispute.
There was immense love and a lot of support for him.
It was packed with people applauding.
It was truly one of the most moving scenes I've ever seen.
Everyone moved aside as he passed.
All those wonderful Londoners who told him
"Hello Charlie"
Or
"Welcome Charlie".
But the British already know that the United States has refused to give him his return visa.
SO,
at the press conference for the film,
The filmmaker will have to react.
The English gave him a warm welcome.
as always.
But they were also on the defensive.
They were very shocked, even in Parliament.
We talked about how the Americans treated him.
Chaplin
tries to get out of it with a pirouette.
He was very careful and didn't say anything "bad".
about America.
And he is right to be cautious.
because from the moment of his arrival,
British intelligence services,
MI5,
They begin to monitor him and report to the FBI.
His file was opened in 1952 when the FBI sent a message to MI5 requesting that one of us closely monitor this man.
Charlie Chaplin.
MI5 reacted at the heart of it all.
When the FBI asks for something,
MI5 responds, "Yes,
chief !
Yes,
chef!
Chaplin therefore understands that he is not necessarily welcome in England.
And the news from the United States isn't good either.
His film is hardly being shown anywhere.
The film was not released in major cities.
as
San Francisco,
New York,
Chicago.
Because these were considered anti-American activities,
as they say.
Chaplin has to make a decision.
And he will choose exile.
He will not return to the United States.
He then did everything he could to permanently sever ties with that country.
The priority?
Finding a new home for his family.
He travels around Europe.
and eventually discovers a splendid manor house in Switzerland,
on the shores of Lake Geneva.
It is here at the Banque mansion that Charlie Chaplin will continue his life.
But what is his state of mind?
He was the one who decided not to return to the United States.
But he knows very well that he had no choice.
J.
Edgar Hoover is already presenting his departure as his greatest trophy.
So,
will Chaplin accept this change of life?
He, who has just experienced the glamour of Hollywood for 40 years,
finally decides to cut himself off from the world.
This could be seen as an early retirement,
But Chaplin has no intention of disappearing.
even though for the moment his main concern,
It's his family.
Ouna,
his wife,
is pregnant with their fifth child.
I had my father bring us here.
To see the house,
What is the house?
And it was impressive.
The sale went very quickly, as is often the case.
Everything that Mr.
Chaplin,
It was fate.
Chaplin thus found a home for his family.
He now has to repatriate all his belongings left in Hollywood.
Basically,
They had only left with the essentials for their vacation.
Nothing more.
They had left all their possessions behind.
They didn't know if they were going to be confiscated or what was going to happen.
He can no longer leave.
SO,
He sends Una to Los Angeles to manage their assets.
Before leaving,
She put everything under her own name.
She sold the house.
the furniture,
All of that.
Ouna had to go through a very difficult time.
She was forced to surrender her American passport.
To accompany her husband to the very end,
Ouna agrees to take British citizenship.
At the end of 1954,
All of Charlie Chaplin's films were repatriated to London and his fortune to Switzerland.
At 65,
He is starting a new life.
He reconnects with his brother Sidney.
who comes to spend many summers at the manor.
Since his departure from the United States,
He married a gypsy woman and travels the world in a caravan.
Chaplin also organized large banquets with visiting friends.
Hollywood veterans,
stars from all over Europe.
He finally gives the impression of letting life happen.
He was very bitter about the United States,
But he was happy to be living in Switzerland with Una and the children in a very beautiful house.
They were free.
They have travelled a lot.
Their lives were very full.
He became a bon vivant, and I think that was true throughout his life before that.
It was really the job.
This film industry and all the worries about continuing,
to produce something,
He discovered life from a slightly different perspective.
And I think it did him a lot of good.
I think he was very happy.
And the family is growing.
In total,
Ouna will give him eight children.
Their new life has the appearance of a fairy tale.
But deep down,
Chaplin suffers from no longer being the man he once was.
He misses cinema and is gradually getting back to work.
He was very afraid of being forgotten by the public.
that people are no longer interested in him,
that he is a has-been,
outdated.
He was still afraid of becoming poor again despite having a considerable fortune.
On two occasions,
Chaplin is trying to make a comeback.
In 1957,
He is writing and directing a new film.
A king in New York.
An anti-American diatribe that will never be shown in the United States.
This film will primarily result in the return of wiretapping.
openness to tenacious hatred,
The FBI even manages to convince the Swiss to keep an eye on Chaplin.
The Swiss government bugged his house.
There was a microphone in the phone.
The Swiss secret services were terribly cooperative with the FBI.
They were sending information constantly.
They were watched until the very end.
That is to say, we have records up to 1978.
Thank you.
Chaplin is filming one last movie.
in 1967,
The Countess of Hong Kong.
Two stars have agreed to join him in his project.
Sophia Loren and Marlon Brando.
For him, it was surely a kind of return to his youth from the good old days.
But it's also the pleasure of working with the biggest stars of the time,
Brando and Sophia Loren.
They immediately agreed to work with Charlie Chaplin.
But the filming goes badly.
Chaplin and Brando did not get along.
They will put on a good show until the end of the film.
but they will no longer speak to each other.
They were two great men who were not meant to work together.
The film is a failure.
Yet,
Chaplin persists.
He locks himself in his office to write new screenplays and spends entire days at the piano reworking the music for his films.
Recomposing film scores,
at that time,
We absolutely mustn't move.
Don't make any noise.
Yes,
a child who was running down the stairs a little.
Too loudly,
Well then,
It was the severe and rigid side that stood out in the old Victorian man.
Everyone around him understood that he needed to be left alone.
Music,
writing,
the films,
That's what keeps him alive.
For some time now,
She is a woman in love.
Ouna,
who has made a habit of filming Charlie,
to capture their life at the manor on film.
For me,
it was an example of love,
of infinite love between the two.
He now spends most of his time with her.
Chaplin still planned a moment each day when he devoted himself entirely to his children.
It was necessary to be there and very present.
At mealtimes,
if you missed even 5 minutes during the meal,
Well, you don't eat.
With them,
Chaplin is often harsh.
He had trouble seeing us.
we children,
in this luxury,
whereas he had really had to fight,
child.
And that stood out.
he told us,
But all that,
overnight,
It can disappear.
He believed that education,
It was the only weapon.
Really,
to defend oneself in life.
But Chaplin will also teach them the art of disguise and comedy.
I feel nostalgic for that childhood that I adored.
I regret not being a teenager or a child anymore.
Over the years...
They will all leave the manor to live their lives.
sometimes also fleeing from this paternal figure,
imposing.
In the early 1970s,
Chaplin's great classics are being re-released in theaters.
20 years after his exile,
His visionary genius is finally being recognized.
The filmmaker is invited around the world to receive a flood of awards.
At the end of his life,
He was very eager for recognition.
He was very old,
Therefore, the grudges and old grudges of the past,
They're kind of being overlooked.
In London,
He makes peace with the British secret services.
Chaplin was then received at Buckingham Palace to be honored by the Queen of England.
He loved becoming Sister Charles.
because we mustn't forget where he comes from.
And what he accomplished,
and to be recognized by one's own country.
It's really very beautiful.
He was very proud.
Can you imagine,
A child from the working-class neighborhoods who succeeded and meets the queen.
He must have seen that with a great deal of irony.
because the queen,
She should have received it when he came from America.
That would be a wonderful gesture.
He said, "There you go."
We disagree with you.
He is a great director.
Well,
she didn't.
All these awards have sparked renewed interest in Chaplin.
In February 1973,
American director Peter Bogdanovich decided to dedicate a documentary to him and came to interview him at his home.
in Vevey.
But it's too late.
At 84 years old,
Age and fatigue have taken their toll on his memory, and the old man is unable to recount the tormented story of his genius.
What I was thinking,
it was
Fred Carnot,
Isn't that right?
Who started with the troupe.
And people like that,
or Max Sennett.
I can't think of anyone right now.
I could,
later,
i guess.
But I can't think of just anyone.
How did you...
Have you worked with Jackie Coogan?
I don't know,
I don't remember.
Hollywood,
success,
women,
the torments.
Chaplin seems to have forgotten everything.
All,
with the exception of his childhood.
You had a rather unhappy childhood.
This is about the Kni Circus's visit to Vevey.
In October 1977,
while he hardly moves from his armchair,
He insists once again that we take him there.
It was clear he wasn't doing well.
But still,
He absolutely wanted to see the show.
And we said,
He is so tired,
But he wanted to come to the circus.
absolutely.
We,
during the show,
always,
Flowers were brought for Onin.
and him,
He was laughing like a madman,
and every year,
We did that.
And he was still laughing.
It was wonderful.
because the Knin,
They were expected at intermission or at the end of the show in their caravan.
Sometimes,
He stayed until two o'clock in the morning.
the following day,
to talk with the clowns,
with the artists,
He loved it.
He went very far back into his childhood.
when he went to the circus.
In the twilight of his life,
Chaplin did not forget the magic of the circus.
But he also retained some less happy childhood memories.
Christmas,
For example.
A date,
a party he never could stand.
He didn't like it.
No.
It depressed him.
I'm thinking about that.
There were too many memories at Christmas.
He must have gone through something terrible.
the child.
When he lived in London,
Chaplin was not entitled to a dinner,
nor to gifts.
He likes to remind his children that his only pleasure that evening was an orange.
I felt we received far too many gifts.
thanks to my mother.
It had become a bit,
I believe,
It's a myth to say...
"Don't show your presents to Dad because it will depress him,"
because he thinks it's a waste of money.
"That didn't stop us from having fun,"
But still.
On December 24, 1977,
Chaplin is particularly tired.
But as usual,
Ouna had big plans.
The whole family is gathered in Vevey.
"It was the big Christmas case."
There was a large fir tree at the entrance,
The gifts.
everywhere,
He really spoiled us.
That evening,
Chaplin cannot finish the evening with the whole family.
He then asked to be escorted to his room.
Ouna leaves her door ajar so he can hear the children's shouts when they open their presents.
But in the early hours of December 25, 1977,
He fell peacefully into his sleep.
That's
where I saw my mother cry for the first time in my life.
She never did it in front of us.
That was a terrible shock for me.
It happens if the timing is right.
He left at Christmas.
Until my last breath,
Chaplin's life was therefore marked by irony.
The one that allowed him to depict the world and its suffering with humor and tenderness.
The one who helped him respond to the attacks.
The one who gave life to Charlie Chaplin and made him immortal.
Strangely,
He will never be lacking.
Chaplin,
since he may no longer be here,
but his work,
his invention,
It will always make people happy.
sad,
It will always affect people.
So it's alive.
somewhere.
If anyone deserves the term genius,
That's definitely Chaplin.
Without a doubt.
A quote from Stéphane Sfaye that I've always really liked,
It is "Men need gods to exist,
But the gods need certain men to prove they exist.
I think Chappie is very much a part of it.
Life can be wonderful if you
Don't be afraid.
Everything you need,
That's courage.
imagination and a little finger.
The hydra has shown so many faces,
The hilarious Charlie Chaplin,
the sad Calvéro,
the man who loved women,
young,
too young
the vanquisher of the powerful,
the extremely wealthy adventurer,
Hollywood's enfant terrible and the solitary recluse of Vevey.
Attempting to uncover the truth of genius always requires looking beyond.
The evening dedicated to Charlie Chaplin and the 100th anniversary of Charlot continues on France 2 with a film,
one of his greatest masterpieces.
You have just discovered what goes on behind the scenes,
here is...
The Dictator,
his most visionary film,
written in 1936 and published in 1940,
He perceived the dangers of Hitler's madness before anyone else.
See you very soon.